Register of the Ardashīr Zāhidī papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Minister of Foreign Affairs File, 1965-1971
  - Ramsar Conference records, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 10-13)
    Documents related to a meeting between the Shah, President Ayub Khan of Pakistan, and Prime Minister Süleyman Demirel of Turkey. Includes transcipts from discussions, shared statement from the three leaders, Zahedi's notes and talking points, as well as notes from other individuals, and hotel information. Topics of discussion include Regional Cooperation for Development (RCD), CENTO, Western and Soviet influence in the Middle East, and Arab countries in the Middle East.
  - Marzbān-Petrochemistry, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    Includes correspondence between Zahedi and Manouchehr Marzban and information about Allied Chemical.
  - Ramsar Conference, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    Ramsar discussions. Includes photocopy of report from previous Ramsar file, and information about Goronwy Roberts.
  - Correspondence with the British Secretary of State on the Persian Gulf Federation, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Draft of shared statement between Iran and the Soviet Union, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    Includes report written by Amir-Abbas Hoveyda to the Shah.
  - Military talks with Pakistan, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    Includes documents relating to talks regarding military and political cooperation between Iran and Pakistan, including speeches, meeting agendas, "Joint Report by the Military Committee," and communications between the Iranian Ministry of Foreign Affairs and the Embassy of Pakistan in Iran. Lieutenant General Fereydoun Djam and Air Marshal Malik Nur Khan participated in the talks.
  - Ethiopia visit, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    Includes notes from discussions between the Shah and Emperor Haile Selassie, and Zahedi and Foreign Minister Ketema Yifru.
  - Coronation, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    Includes notes written by Zahedi, memos and reports, and text from media interview with the Shah.
  - Purchase of arms, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    Includes a photocopy of a letter to Zahedi from the Ministry of War and accompanying papers.
  - Soviet planes over Iran, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    Includes communications between Zahedi and Ambassador Ahmad Mirfendereski, between the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and the Iraqi Embassy in Tehran, memos from Zahedi to the Shah, and notes from talks between the Shah and the Soviet ambassador.
  - CENTO talks with the American ambassadors in Tehran and in Kabul, 1966-1967 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Includes letters, transcript notes from talks between Zahedi, Armin H. Meyer, Robert G. Neumann; and Zahedi's notes to the Shah; and transcripts from other CENTO talks.
  - Talks between the Shah and the British Foreign Minister, 1965 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Talks between the Shah and the President of Iraq, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    Includes documents related to the 1967 Iraq state visit to Iran, including notes from discussions between the Shah and President Abdul Rahman Arif, between Zahedi and Foreign Minister Adnan Pachachi, Zahedi's notes and talking points, as well as a draft joint communique.
  - Talks between the Shah, the Prime Minister of Iran, and the Prime Minister of Iraq, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
    Includes communications between Zahedi and Amir Khosrow Afshar, transcipts from talks between the Shah, Amir-Abbas Hoveyda, Tahir Yahya, Amir Khosrow Afshar and ʻAbd al-Jabbār Shanshal, and a draft communique.
  - Tahir Yahya's Iran visit, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    Includes notes from a meeting with Hoveyda, and a shared statement by the two countries.
  - Talks between the Shah and Ayub Khan, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    Includes transcripts from talks between the Shah and Ayub Khan, between Zahedi and Mian Arshad Hussain, and a joint communique.
  - Talks between the Shah and the Foreign Minister Kuwait, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Talks with Dr. Eghbal in Jeddah, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    Includes transcripts from talks between Dr. Manouchehr Eghbal (Manūchihr Iqbāl), Head of the Iranian National Oil Company; Ahmed Zaki Yamani, Saudi Minister of Oil; and King Faisal.
  - Constitution of East Germany, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    Includes a copy of a letter from Walter Ulbricht to the Shah.
  - Talks between Zahedi and the Foreign Minister of Israel, 1968-1970 (Box 10, Folder 11-12)
  - Talks between Zahedi and the Sheikh of Ras al-Khaimah, 1969-1970 (Box 10, Folder 13-16)
    Also includes transcipts from talks between the Shah, the Prime Minister, and Abbas Aram with the Emir of Ras al-Khaimah, largely on the Tunb Islands.
  - Correspondence with the Foreign Minister of Kuwait, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Talks between Zahedi and the Foreign Minister of Pakistan, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Audience with the Soviet ambassador, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    Includes communications with Hushang Ansary and Abbas Aram.
  - Audience with the Sheikh of Ras al-Khaimah, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Talks between the Shah and the Chancellor of Germany, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Talks between Zahedi and the Sheikh of Fujairah, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence between the Shah and King Hussein, 1969 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Talks between the Prime Minister and the Chancellor of Germany, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Talks between the Shah and the Prime Minister of Afghanistan, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Bahrain, 1968-1970 (Box 12, Folder 1-14, Box 11, Folder 6-26)
    Includes transcripts from negotiations between Iran, Bahrain, and Great Britain; internal talks in the Iranian Ministry of Foreign Affairs; communications between Zahedi, Amir Khosrow Afshar, Mehdi Vekil, Abbas Ali Khalatbari, Mohsen Esfandiari, and Faridun Zandfard; communications between the Iranian Ministry of Foreign Affairs and United Nations Secretary General U Thant; and a copy of an opinion drafted by Robert Yewdall Jennings and Dr. Barrett.
  - Talks between the Shah and the Kremlin, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    Includes transcripts from discussions with Nikolai Podgorny and Alexei Kosygin.
  - Talks between the Prime Minister of Iran and the Prime Minister and King of Afghanistan, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 16-18)
    Includes reports and summaries of talks, drafts of agreements, memos, and a joint communique. Subjects include the Helmand River.
  - Talks between the Prime Minister and the Prime Minister of Romania, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Talks with Richard Nixon, 1967-1968 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Talks between the Shah and King Faisal in Jeddah, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Talks between Zahedi and the Foreign Minister of Kuwait, 1968-1970 (Box 12, Folder 22-24)
    Also includes transcipts from talks between Zahedi and Emir Sabah Al-Salim Al-Sabah, and Saad Al-Salim Al-Sabah, Minister of the Interior.
  - Talks between Zahedi and the Foreign Minister of Saudi Arabia, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    Includes notes and stranscripts from talks between the Shah and King Faisal, and Zahedi and the Minister of Foreign Affairs of Kuwait.
  - Talks between Zahedi and the Foreign Minister of Romania, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Talks between the Shah and Hardan al-Tikriti, Vice President of Iraq, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - RCD talks in Karachi, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Talks between Zahedi and the Prince of Qatar, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Talks between the Shah and the Prime Minister of India, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Talks between Zahedi and the Foreign Minister of Romania, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    Includes a draft of a speech delivered by Zahedi.
  - General Kanwar Zorawar Singh, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Hadi Sepehr, the Arya Party, circa 1968-1969 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - RCD talks in Karachi, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Talks with Franz Josef Strauss, Federal Minister of Finance of Germany, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Committee for Military Cooperation between Iran and Pakistan, 1969-1971 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    Includes communications between Zahedi and Fereydoun Djam, Head of the Iranian Imperial Army Corps, and a transcipt from talks between Hoveyda and Malik Nur Khan.
  - Talks with the King of Malaysia, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - ʻAbd al-Ghanī Akrādī, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Talks between the Shah and United States Secretary of State, William P. Rogers, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Talks between the Shah and the Foreign Minister of Turkey, 1969-1971 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Talks between the Shah and the British Foreign Minister, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 17)
    Also includes transcript from talks between Zahedi and British Foreign Secretary Michael Stewart.
  - Talks between the Shah and the Foreign Minister of India, 1969-1971 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    Also includes transcipts from talks between Zahedi and Swaran Singh, Foreign Minister of India.
  - Talks between Zahedi and Edward Heath, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Talks between Zahedi and Harold H. Saunders, assistant to Henry Kissinger, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Talks between the Shah and Nicolae Ceausescu, President of Romania, 1969-1970 (Box 13, Folder 21-22)
    Also includes a joint communique, and transcript from talks between Zahedi and the Romanian Minister of Foreign Affairs.
  - Talks between Zahedi and the Director of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Japan, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - Talks between the Shah and the Ambassador of Saudi Arabia, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - Meetings with Muhammad Youssef al-Najjar, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 25)
    Includes a copy of a letter from Yasser Arafat to the Shah.
  - Talks between the Shah's Ambassador in Moscow and Vladimir Vinogradov, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 26-28)
    Includes communications between Zahedi and Ahmad Mirfendereski, translations of an interview given by the Shah, and reports on Radio Baghdad.
  - Report from the Shah's ambassador in Kuwait on the activities of Ba'athists, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Talks between the Shah and Abdul-Monem Rifai, 1969-1970 (Box 14, Folder 2-4)
    Includes reports, transcripts, notes, and correspondence related to talks between Iran and Jordan and the Shatt al-Arab dispute between Iran and Iraq.
  - Assistance to Fatah, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Talks between Abbas Ali Khalatbari and the King of Greece, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Talks with the Sheikh of Dubai, 1970 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Talks between Zahedi, Sayyid Muḥammad Yūsuf, and Malik Nur Khan, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Talks with Yahya Khan and Malik Nur Khan, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Talks between the Shah and Malik Nur Khan, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Talks between the Prime Minister and Malik Nur Khan, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 11-12)
  - Arab-Israeli War, 1967 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    Includes communications between Zahedi and Amir Khosrow Afshar, and letters to the King of Jordan and General Abdul Rahman Arif.
  - Nāṭiq Muḥammad Muṣṭafā al-Ṭāʼī, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 14-15)
    Includes communications between Zahedi and Iranian diplomats to Kuwait and Nematollah Nassiri, and copies of Nāṭiq Muḥammad Muṣṭafā al-Ṭāʼī's travel documents.
  - Talks with Michael Stewart, British Foreign Secretary, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 16-19)
  - Talks between the President of Pakistan and the Prime Minister of Iran, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - Talks between Zahedi and Zulfikar Ali Bhutto, 1969-1971 (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - Talks between the Shah and Mitchell Sharp, Foreign Minister of Canada, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 22)
  - Talks between the Shah and Pál Losonczi, Chairman of the Hungarian Presidential Council, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 23)
  - Talks with President Ludvík Svoboda and the Foreign Minister of Czechoslovakia, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 24)
  - Provision of weapons to Saudi Arabia, 1969-1970 (Box 14, Folder 25-26, Box 15, Folder 1)
    Includes communications between the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, between Zahedi and the Foreign Minister of Saudi Arabia, and transcipts from discussions with the Ambassadors of the United States and Saudi Arabia to Iran.
  - Talks with the Sheikh of Sharjah, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 2-3)
    Subjects include Abu Musa Island.
  - Talks with British Parliament member Julian Amery, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Talks with George Brown, previous Foreign Minister of Great Britain, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Talks between the Shah, the Soviet Ambassador, and General Yahya Khan, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    Subjects include Iran-Iraq relations and the Persian Gulf.
  - Talks with Nikolai Podgorny, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Talks with the Sheikh of Qatar, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Talks between Zahedi and the Foreign Minister of Libya, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Talks with King Faisal and the Foreign Minister of Saudi Arabia, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Talks between Zahedi and Dawālībī, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Report on secret CENTO meeting, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    Includes texts of speeches given by the Shah.
  - Talks with the Emir of Abu Dhabi, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Talks between Zahedi and William P. Rogers, United States Secretary of State, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Robert L. F. Sikes, circa 1970 (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Talks with Orhan Eralp, Secretary-General of the Foreign Ministry of Turkey, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Talks between the Shah and Alec Douglas-Home, British Foreign Secretary, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Talks between the Shah and Mohammad Nur Ahmad Etemadi, Prime Minister of Afghanistan, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - Talks between the Shah and Sir William Luce, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 19-21)
  - Talks with the Foreign Minister of Italy, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 22)
    Includes transcripts from talks between the Shah, Zahedi, and Aldo Moro, and a joint communique.
  - Talks with the Foreign Minister of the Netherlands, 1971 (Box 15, Folder 23)
  - Talks with the Foreign Minister of Morocco, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Talks between Zahedi and General Yahya Khan, 1971 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Talks with the Foreign Minister of Tunisia, 1971 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Talks with the President and Foreign Minister of Yugoslavia, 1971 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Meetings with the King of Morocco, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Meeting with Khaled al-Hassan, Representative of the Palestine Liberation Organization, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Talks with Agha Hilaly, Ambassador of Pakistan to the United States, 1971 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Talks between Zahedi and Sheikh Mujibur Rahman, Leader of the Awami League, 1971 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Talks between the Shah and Pierre Trudeau, Prime Minister of Canada, 1971 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Talks between Zahedi and the Foreign Minister of Turkey, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 10-11)
    Subjects include Iraq and Kurds.
  - Talks between Zahedi and Yaḥyá Rifʻa from the Egyptian embassy, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence with Parviz Khonsari, 1969-1970 (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Speeches, 1967-1971
    - "Compilation of Speeches by His Excellency Ardeshir Zahedi,", 1967-1971 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - CENTO Ministerial Council opening statements, 1968-1971 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - RCD Ministerial Council opening statements, 1967-1971 (Box 16, Folder 16-18)
    - United Nations General Assembly opening statements, 1967-1970 (Box 16, Folder 19-20)
  - Financial records, 1967-1970 (Box 16, Folder 21-24)
    Includes reports, receipts, payments, correspondence, and notes related to the workings and expenses of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and the Iranian Consulate in Geneva.
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1968-1972 (Box 16, Folder 25)
    Includes information regarding the accompanying of Princess Bilqis Begum, a resume, and a letter.
- Switzerland File, 1968-1973
  During the time between his post as Minister of Foreign Affairs and second appointment as Ambassador to the United States, Zahedi resided in the Villa les Roses in Montreux, Switzerland.
  - Correspondence, 1968-1973
    - Outgoing, circa 1972 (Box 17, Folder 1)
      Three letters; addressed to Asadollah Alam, the Shah, and Shahnaz Pahlavi.
    - Incoming, 1972-1973 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Mushīrī, ʻAlī, 1968-1972 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Qurayshī, Aḥmad, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Vakīl, Mahdī, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 5)
      Also spelled Mehdi Vakil.
    - Yigānah, Muḥammad, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 6)
      Also spelled Mohammad Yeganeh.
    - Telegrams and cards, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 7-11)
      Includes telegraphs and cards related to Nawruz, 28th of Mordad, Zahedi's birthday, other holidays, and the anniversary of his father's death.
- Ambassador to the United States File, 1970-1979
  - Rāhnamā-yi bāygānī, 1973-1979 (Box 17, Folder 12-13)
    Inventory for documents from Zahedi's second appointment as Ambassador to the United States, as they were housed in his home in Montreux, Switzerland.
  - Embassy files, 1970-1978
    Correspondence, documents, memoranda, notes, reports, speeches, and printed matter from Zahedi's second appointment as Ambassador to the United States. Correspondence files include accompanying printed matter and Iranian government correspondence. Original order, correspondence groups, and folder titles have been maintained, and many individuals have multiple correspondence files.
    Subjects include Iranian-American relations, Iranian foreign policy, Middle Eastern politics, Iran and the Shah as portrayed in the media, political developments in the United States, oil and energy, economic issues, the purchase of arms, human rights in Iran, embassy activities and social events, the Hanafi Siege, Iranian dissent in the United States, unrest in Iran, state visits, and gifts.
    - Documents reviewed by the Shah, 1973-1979
      "Sharaf ʻarz̤ī pīshgāh-i mubārak-i Shāhanshāh Āryā Mihr."
      Includes reports and communications addressed or forwarded to the Shah, Zahedi's correspondence, Zahedi's notes, communications between the embassy and the Special Bureau, media reports, some photographs, and accompanying printed material. Materials are mostly in English and Persian, with some items in Spanish and French. Correspondents include American politicians, military and intelligence officials, journalists and people working in news media, academics, and business leaders, as well as diplomats and political figures from other countries. Many of the correspondents have files in the following correspondence groups, and some of the letters are duplicated within these correspondence groupings.
      Iranian correspondents include Yūsuf Akbar, Assad Homayoun, Abbas Ali Khalatbari, Nosratollah Moeinian, ʻAbbās Ordubādi, and Jamshīd Tavallalī.
      - 1973 (Box 18, Folder 1-4)
      - 1973-1974 (Box 18, Folder 5)
      - 1974 (Box 18, Folder 6-18, Box 19, Folder 1-8)
      - 1974-1975 (Box 19, Folder 9-11)
      - 1975 (Box 20, Folder 1-13, Box 19, Folder 12-17)
      - 1975-1976 (Box 20, Folder 14-18)
      - 1976 (Box 20, Folder 19, Box 238, Box 21, Folder 1-16)
      - 1976-1977 (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - 1977 (Box 22, Folder 2-18, Box 23, Folder 1-14)
      - 1977-1978 (Box 23, Folder 15-17, Box 24, Folder 1-3)
      - 1978 (Box 25, Folder 1-4, Box 24, Folder 4-15)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 25, Folder 5-6)
    - Telegraph books, 1973-1978
      Printed compilations of telegraphs from the embassy to the Vizārat-i Umūr-i Khārijah (Ministry of Foreign Affairs), Vizārat-i Darbār-i Shāhanshāhī (Ministry of Royal Court), and Daftar-i Makhṣūṣ (Special Bureau). Books are indexed with tables of contents, with subject titles for each telegraph.
      Subjects include American foreign relations, American internal politics, Watergate, American media reporting, oil, Middle Eastern politics, the Arab-Israeli conflict, Iranian foreign relations, Soviet politics, state visits, social events, and meetings.
      - Guzārishhā-yi siyāsī-yi tiligrāfī bih Vizārat-i Umūr-i Khārijah-i Shāhanshāhī 1352, 1973-1974 (Box 26)
      - Guzārishhā-yi siyāsī-yi tiligrāfī bih Vizārat-i Umūr-i Khārijah-i Shāhanshāhī 1353-1354, 1974-1976 (Box 27)
      - Guzārishhā-yi siyāsī-yi tiligrāfī bih Vizārat-i Umūr-i Khārijah-i Shāhanshāhī 1355-1356, 1976-1978 (Box 27)
      - Guzārishhā-yi siyāsī-yi tiligrāfī bih Vizārat-i Darbār-i Shāhanshāhī va-Daftar-i Makhṣūṣ-i Shāhanshāhī 1352, 1973-1974 (Boxes 27-28)
      - Guzārishhā-yi siyāsī-yi tiligrāfī bih Vizārat-i Darbār-i Shāhanshāhī va-Daftar-i Makhṣūṣ-i Shāhanshāhī 1353, 1974-1975 (Box 28)
      - Guzārishhā-yi siyāsī-yi tiligrāfī bih Vizārat-i Darbār-i Shāhanshāhī va-Daftar-i Makhṣūṣ-i Shāhanshāhī 1354, 1975-1976 (Box 29)
      - Guzārishhā-yi siyāsī-yi tiligrāfī bih Vizārat-i Darbār-i Shāhanshāhī va-Daftar-i Makhṣūṣ-i Shāhanshāhī 1355, 1976-1977 (Box 29)
      - Guzārishhā-yi siyāsī-yi tiligrāfī bih Vizārat-i Darbār-i Shāhanshāhī va-Daftar-i Makhṣūṣ-i Shāhanshāhī 1356, 1977-1978 (Box 30)
      - Envelopes, 1973-1978 (Boxes 31-32, 236)
        With embassy seals.
    - Shah's correspondence, 1970-1978
      Copies of the Shah's correspondence with American presidents, politicians, journalists, and business figures.
      - Richard M. Nixon, 1970-1978 (Box 33, Folder 1-6)
      - Gerald R. Ford, 1974-1977 (Box 33, Folder 7-12)
      - Jimmy Carter, 1977-1978 (Box 33, Folder 13-18, Box 34, Folder 1-2)
      - Other, 1971-1978 (Box 34, Folder 3-5)
        Includes correspondence with Richard Helms, Hubert Humphrey, J.K. Jamieson, Robert McNamara, Nelson Rockefeller, Cyrus Vance, Barbara Walters, and the King of Saudi Arabia.
    - Talks between the Shah and Zulfikar Ali Bhutto, 1973-1975 (Box 34, Folder 6)
    - Talks between the Shah and the President of Mexico, 1975 (Box 34, Folder 7)
    - Talks between the Shah and others, 1973-1977 (Box 34, Folder 8-12)
      Includes notes and transcripts from talks between the Shah and Nicolae Ceaușescu, Alec Douglas-Home, Vladimir Erofeev, Richard Helms, Alexei Kosygin, Nelson Rockefeller, William P. Rogers, and Todor Zhivkov, as well as talks between Khalatbari and Ḥasan Muḥammad Makkī.
    - Department of Defense, 1973-1975 (Box 34, Folder 13)
      Mostly correspondence between the Shah and Secretary of Defense James R. Schlesinger.
    - Central Intelligence Agency, 1974-1975 (Box 34, Folder 14)
      Includes correspondence between Zahedi and William E. Colby.
    - National Security Council, 1976-1978 (Box 34, Folder 15)
      Largely correspondence between Zahedi and Brent Scowcroft, and Zbigniew Brzezinski.
    - Secretary of State Cyrus Vance, 1977-1978 (Box 34, Folder 16)
      Includes transcripts from discussions with Kissinger, and communications between Zahedi and the Shah with Gerald Ford.
    - Purchase of arms, 1974 (Box 34, Folder 17)
    - Ḥasan Ṭūfāniyān, 1972-1977 (Box 34, Folder 18-21, Box 35, Folder 1)
      Also spelled Hassan Toufanian. Correspondence with and about Toufanian, and documents and correspondence related to Iranian purchase of weapons from the United States.
    - Muḥammad Amīr Khātamī, 1975 (Box 35, Folder 2)
      Correspondence, notes, and reports related to defense and weapons.
    - Bahrain, 1974 (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - Nuclear-free zone in the Middle East, 1974 (Box 35, Folder 4-6)
    - Talks with Ashraf Ghorbal, 1973 (Box 35, Folder 7-8)
      Subjects include Arab-Israeli conflict.
    - Talks with Henry Kissinger, 1974-1977 (Box 35, Folder 9)
      Includes reports from talks between Zahedi and President Ford, as well as copies of letters from the Shah to Ford.
    - Ajax, Undated (Box 35, Folder 10)
      Copy of "Smith draft" forwarded from Kermit Roosevelt.
    - Iranian agents in the United States, 1977-1978 (Box 35, Folder 11)
      Includes a copy of a memorandum from the Federal Bureau of Investigation.
    - Zahedi in Brazil, 1974 (Box 35, Folder 12-13)
      Consists of documents related to Iranian diplomatic presence at Ernesto Geisel's inauguration.